OK, let's get started.
So today is the second day on data.
Last time we talked about how data doesn't really
just fall from the sky.
You actually have to think about where it comes from.
So in general, the internet consists of live services.
That data on those services have to be either dumped or crawled.
And then there's an additional step where
you have to process the data.
And we also talked about various societal considerations,
terms of service, copyright.
You have to either get a license or appeal to fair use.
So there's a lot of complexity that goes into data.
So today we're going to look more at the data pipeline
from transforming the data, filtering the data,
deduplication, and mixing.
And then we're going to top it off
by talking a bit about post-training data,
in particular, how folks are using synthetic data these days.
So the first part is going to be mostly about pre-training.
That's what you should have in mind.
So we talked a little bit about data transformation already,
but just as a reminder.
So raw data doesn't come as text, even as
if you've scraped something.
If you ever look inside Common Crawl, it's not text.
It's either HTML.
Sometimes it could be PDFs or directories
in the case of GitHub.
So most of the attention on transforming data
is dealing with HTML because most of the web is in HTML.
And for this processing, a lot of this is fairly heuristic.
There's removing of boilerplate, like navigation and ads,
and extracting content, which is the main part of the page.
And there's some subtleties around what constitutes content.
Usually, you get rid of the footers and headers, and maybe
menus, and those things, and you try to extract the content.
But you could imagine in cases where
some of the navigation elements might
be helpful to learn what web pages look like.
So what is content and what is not content is not always clear.
And then what do you do about images and tables that
are in web pages?
So inherently, this is a lossy process
because you need to linearize HTML, which at least is
either hierarchical or visual, if you
think about the rendered output, and to a sequence of tokens.
And particularly tables are a bit tricky to deal with.
Simple tables, you can render using Markdown.
But if you have nested tables, then that
becomes quite challenging.
You have to give up at some point
or approximate at some point.
So, typically, HTML to text processing is rule-based.
And the reason for this is that rule-based processors
are very fast.
And also, you're not trying to do too much here.
You don't need too much intelligence.
So rule-based generally works.
Now, I think there could be a case
for model-based interventions at this point.
They have to be very fast, and they
have to do something more intelligent.
But if you ever look at data, you'll
notice there are imperfections in the data
just because any rule-based processing has some failure
rate.
As we showed last time, the accuracy
does matter, depending on which tool you choose.
If you use Resiliparse or Trafilatura, then--
I guess Resiliparse on these extended dclm evals
works better than the others.
I'll talk also briefly about PDFs.
So there's Hugging Face work, which released
a data set called FinePDFs.
So PDF files, if you ever opened them up, not in a PDF reader,
looks like this, and this needs to get rendered.
So PDFs can be found on just web pages on the internet.
And Common Crawl does have some PDFs.
Generally, Common Crawl focuses on text,
but sometimes, if you're just given a URL,
you might not even know before you fetch it whether it's a PDF
or not, if it doesn't have the extension.
If you read this blog post, there's
a lot of details, which I'll spare you of.
For example, one thing is that many of the PDFs
that are in Common Crawl are truncated because PDFs are big,
so then that demands that recrawling is necessary.
And then there's a question: once you have the PDF file,
how do you actually convert it to text?
And some PDFs might be just scans as well.
So they're essentially images.
So there's a bunch of tools that this paper tried out,
but mostly this involves running OCR using a VLM.
And this obviously can be much more expensive than what
we were doing before with text.
Fortunately or unfortunately, the PDFs
are a very small fraction of the whole internet.
But they are very valuable because generally,
if you bother to make a PDF, that means you probably
have something interesting to say as opposed to a web page.
So the quality of an average PDF is generally higher
than for an HTML file.
There's a lot of cleanup and filtering.
And PDFs, more so even than web pages,
a lot of layout information is missing,
because in HTML you have various tags like h1 and p
that gives you some semantic information.
PDFs are, by design, all about layout.
So you don't necessarily preserve the semantic structure.
So there's a bunch of transformation that happens.
At this point, you have text, but you're not done.
You're far from done.
So the next step is filtering.
So I'm going to talk somewhat abstractly about what filtering
is.
Here's the building block.
So suppose you have some target data that you want to get.
This is usually a small amount of high-quality data and lots
of raw data.
This is the fresh shipment of the tokens
that you transformed from the previous step.
And the goal is to find a subset of this raw data that
is similar to target.
So this is the general skeleton for filtering,
and almost all kinds of filtering falls into this schema.
So filtering, there's many reasons you might want to filter.
If you're training an English language
model or a German language model,
you might want to identify the language and filter things that
don't match that language.
The main reason for filtering is quality filtering.
You want to find things that are high quality as opposed
to low quality.
You don't want just spam.
You want encyclopedic information.
And then another application is toxicity filtering.
Of course, the internet has plenty of nasty content,
and maybe you don't want to train your language
model on that.
So, for a filtering algorithm, you want some generalization
from the target data, because you already
have the target data.
You don't want to only get the target data,
but you also want it to be extremely fast
because you have to run it on the whole internet.
So this could be 100 trillion tokens worth of data.
So generally, filtering is you end up
with a very small fraction, a single-digit fraction
of your entire data.
OK.
So remember the general framework
given the target, and raw, you're trying to find a subset.
So the general scheme is that you estimate some model based
on R and T and derive a scoring function,
and then you keep the examples in R based on their score.
So typically, there are two types of classifiers.
One are generative models.
So this is basically you have your target data.
You can just estimate a model of that data.
And remember, this has to be cheap,
so probably you're not training a big language model.
Generally, KenLM basically says I'm going to train a 5-gram
model.
A more common thing, which I think
we're mostly seeing these days, is just training a classifier.
And the classifier says, I'm going
to predict a positive label, for example,
that are in T, my target, and negative labels
for things that are in raw but not in T.
So basically, it looks like T are your positive examples,
some random subset of R are your negative examples.
Maybe you balance it, and then you train a classifier.
And the tool that people generally use
is fastText because it's fast.
And generally, it's just a linear classifier--
a bag of words.
And then once you have this model now
for every new document, you can score it,
and you set some appropriate threshold,
depending on your quality bar, and you keep the examples.
Sometimes stochastically, sometimes not.
So this is very much a model-based filtering approach.
Remember from the last lecture, there
are many data sets from generally a few years ago
that did not use model-based filtering because they wanted
to not bias things too much.
These days, I think basically everyone
does some amount of model-based filtering
because unless you are compute-plentiful, in which case
you probably don't need to do as much filtering-- you can just
train on everything.
Most people are compute-poor.
You have to be very smart about how you're filtering;
otherwise, you're just wasting flops on low-quality content.
OK, so let me talk through some instantiations of filtering.
So remember, I mentioned language identification.
So the goal is just to find-- given a piece of text,
detect whether it's of a particular language.
So Meta has trained this set of fastText language identification
models, which often you can just use off the shelf.
So it supports 176 different languages.
It's been trained on a bunch of multilingual sites.
So Wikipedia, remember, has a lot of languages.
There's also translation sites and sites
for different languages.
So a language ID is generally a fairly easy problem
compared to many other tasks that we're dealing
with-- so a simple classifier.
If you look at a few words, you can tell
that it's Spanish or Japanese.
Now, there are subtleties because of code-switching
and text, and there's some dialects.
So I wouldn't say it absolutely solved problem,
but this is not really the bottleneck
for training a good language model.
And then you can just-- so once you have your classifier,
you just choose some threshold.
This is generally fairly heuristic.
So another thing you can do with filtering is that,
suppose you're looking for data of a certain type.
So let's say you want to get really good at math,
so you want to go and find a bunch of math data.
So OpenMathText is this paper from 2023,
where the goal is to create a large corpus of math text.
This pipeline consists of a few steps.
So it's not training a single classifier.
So first, you use some rules to filter.
Does it contain latex commands?
They also use KenLM.
So this is a generative approach.
And trained it on the ProofPile, which
is a known data set of math, and keep it
if the perplexity is below some threshold.
And then you also train a fastText classifier
to predict whether it's mathematical writing or not.
And there's two different thresholds
if it has latex in it, then it's a higher bar--
sorry-- it's a lower bar, but if it doesn't have latex in it,
it's a higher bar.
And then, as a result, they got 15 billion tokens,
which they use to train models.
And there's a paper that showed that this more targeted, curated
data collection results in models
that are better at math than models that were trained
on 20 times as much data, which were not filtered in this way.
So the quality filtering again, think about it as a tool.
You can define quality however you want.
There's no universal notion of quality.
If you want to define quality to be math,
then you can go and get math, and you get better at it.
So GPT-3, I think I mentioned this last time,
but just to put it in this framework.
So positive examples are Wikipedia, WebText.
So these are pages that link out from high-star Reddit posts,
and some books.
And negatives are generally sampled from the web.
They train a linear classifier and keep documents
if the linear classifier is scored highly enough.
There's the first LLaMA paper.
The positives were pages referenced by Wikipedia, not
Wikipedia articles themselves.
And it's this same idea.
So phi-1 from Microsoft is interestingly also
falls into this framework.
So they started with-- the raw data is not already
a Python subset of the stack.
Remember this is all code.
And they define a prompt, which determines educational value.
And then they use GPT-4 to classify a subset of R,
100k subset of R with this prompt,
and the ones that are positive are kept and called the target.
So the target here is actually the output
of an expensive classifier.
And then you train a cheaper classifier,
in their case, a Random Forest, but you could have probably
used fastText as well.
And then you select data that is classified positive
by this classifier.
And they also showed that using this data set,
you do much better than if you're just using the raw data.
So this performance goes up in fewer steps to a higher value.
So toxicity works the same way.
There's this Dataset--
Jigsaw Toxic Comments, where it came from this project
where the goal is to help people have better discussions online.
So here the data is the Wikipedia talk pages, which can,
I guess, for controversial sites get quite heated.
And this has been annotated with whether there are
any toxic comments on there.
And you can similarly define positive and negative examples,
and you can train a classifier on that.
So now I think you have the tools, or some examples
and inspiration.
You can identify a particular type of data that you want.
You build a classifier for it, and then you
can go filter Common Crawl for that.
I want to talk about one subtlety here,
which is that-- no, the notion of what you want for data
actually depends on what model you want to train.
So in particular, it depends on the number
of tokens you're training on.
And so there's no optimal threshold.
So before, when I looked at the classifier,
it gives you a score.
You can't say 0.9 and say that's the best because it
depends on what you want to do.
Intuitively, if you are going to train
for a longer period of time, then you
can tolerate lower quality data.
If you're training for shorter, then you
want higher quality data, in general.
And of course, if you could wave a magic wand,
if you're training for longer, you want more high-quality data,
but that's not an option that you're given.
The data pool is what it is.
So here's a preliminary experiment that Michael Ryan did.
So basically, this plot shows for a 157-million parameter
model.
We're taking a very small pool.
So 100 works, which is a tiny fraction of Common Crawl.
And we're training and training for more over time.
So let's take a look at the blue curve.
So the blue curve is dclm.
And so the loss starts here.
And then it comes down.
And each of these lines is when you epoch over the data.
So this is one epoch, and then the next blue
is the second epoch, and so on and so forth.
So there's not that much data.
So eventually, you have to repeat your data.
And the loss continues going down
because the second time you look at the data,
you're still learning things.
And at some point, you start to overfit.
Whereas if you look at Resiliparse,
this is basically no filtering.
So here, it's much worse in the beginning.
But as you continue and continue, at some point,
you also epoch.
It starts to go down slower.
So you see this trend where high-quality data
is better in this regime, where you're not epoching.
But once you get to lots and lots of tokens,
high-quality data is no longer that great.
And of course, with high-quality data,
you wouldn't want to go into this regime
because you're overfitting—you probably stop here.
But even at this point, this is worse
than if you had trained for longer using low-quality data.
Yeah.
Just a question about computing the metrics.
This is actually not totally about the graph.
Each of those dots corresponds with one training run, right?
Yes.
Do you ever need to do the confidence interval when you're
doing these retraining experiments,
or is it enough just to do it one time?
So the question is, each of these points
is a single training run, should you do it multiple times
and get confidence intervals?
Ideally, that would be a good practice.
Often, you'll see in these papers
that these are scarce because each training
run is fairly expensive.
But in reality, when we have done these experiments,
it generally tends to be stable,
I would say, at least for pretraining.
So you mentioned training for longer and high-quality data,
is that not a combination that we're considering?
But if we are training longer on this high-quality data,
would it have diminishing returns
compared to training for longer with the high-quality data?
So the question is, if you were able to get higher quality data
and you trained for longer, would it
still have diminishing returns?
Every data set is going to have diminishing returns eventually.
That's finite.
But it would probably be here.
It would just be down here and just keep on going down.
OK.
Great.
Let's move on.
So summary, filtering is pretty critical for building
a good model, especially when you're compute-constrained
like most of us.
Technically, if you have infinite compute,
you don't need to filter.
And you can train on everything, and it'll be a giant model.
But realistically, everyone has to filter.
So the recipe here is figure out what good data looks like.
And then you can train a classifier,
and that will extrapolate to the rest of your model.
And what good data looks like?
You can either find it by saying,
aha, there's this data set out there that I really like
and I just want more of it.
Or you can craft a prompt to a language
model and then use that to construct,
to do a preliminary filter of a large pool,
and then use that good quality data to train a smaller
classifier and extrapolate to everyone else.
OK.
Next, I'm going to talk about de-duplication.
So at this point, we have filtered our data set.
So we only have what we deem to be high-quality data.
But often, data still has duplicates in it.
And there's two types of duplicates.
There's exact duplicates.
So this happens when, for example,
if you look at these mirror sites,
the whole point of a mirror is that it's a duplicate.
And sometimes the web crawler isn't smart enough
to know that this mirror is exactly this mirror,
so it just crawls many sites, and you'll
get this exact same content.
Also, when you fork a repo, that is also a duplicate,
even if you make changes.
Probably you're making changes to a few files,
so 99% of that repo might be the same.
So duplicate is abundant.
And yeah, sometimes there's actually
near duplicates which are not mirrors or derivative,
but they just happen to be the same text differing
by a few tokens.
Usually, probably this came from--
it could be copying or came from a different common source.
So here are some examples of near duplicates.
So terms of service and licenses.
So I guess the MIT license probably
shows up on a lot of places.
And so in many cases, it is a exact copy,
but only of that license, unless someone made a typo
when they copied it.
But the rest of the page that the license might be part of
might be different.
And we talked about how a lot of websites
have the same headers and footers.
Those are also duplicates.
There's also cases where, for whatever reason,
this is from LM1B, so the 1 billion per benchmark.
There's these articles where you just
have typographic differences.
There's one version with a comma and one version without a comma.
I don't really know why, but that happens.
And sometimes you see these templates
where this is some probably low-quality content, where
it essentially looks like an ad or some sort,
and someone just templatized and replaced Canada with USA.
So if you train on this data, but you are just
training on different variations of this with different entities,
this is going to be wasting your GPUs.
There's a more extreme cases.
So this is why it's good to look at your data.
So this audit of the C4 data set found this product description
61,000 times in the data set.
And if you trace back-- this is really bizarre.
I don't know why.
This is some description of this gas mask.
And this just showed up in this data set in Common Crawl 61,000
times.
So yeah, the web is weird.
So why deduplicate?
So the first idea is clear because you
want to train more efficiently.
Deduplication reduces your data set size
without really losing information because you're just
removing duplicates.
And it also has this benefit of avoiding memorization,
which this paper talks about.
For example, if you have some copyrighted content that's
duplicated a lot, then if you train on it,
then you'll memorize it, and also privacy concerns.
But mostly, I think, it's just to make sure
that you're not wasting flops.
Related to deduplication is also decontamination,
which is arguably even more important, too.
And it's the same deal, is that you
want to make sure that your test set is not in your training set.
So how do we de-dupe?
So here's the design space to think about.
So first of all, what are the items that you're de-duping?
Do you do at the sentence level, the paragraph level,
or the document level?
How do you determine a match?
Is it an exact match?
Is it existence of a common subitem?
Is it the fraction of common subitems for near de-duplication?
And then once you find a duplicate between two pages,
what do you do?
Do you remove all the instances, or do you remove all but one?
And the key algorithmic challenge
is that de-duplication is fundamentally
about comparing items to other items.
And normally, if you're doing filtering,
this is about an individual item.
Is this item good or not?
And this can be parallelized.
It's linear time, which is good.
And even in linear time, we're trying
to make it fast by having rule-based or very small models.
But your de-duplication, clearly, you
can't do the n-squared thing where you compare everything
to everything.
You need linear-time algorithms to scale, especially
at this web scale.
So typically, the de-duplication literature
uses hash functions to get around this.
So we'll develop some of these ideas.
These are quite nice ideas from--
thanks to the algorithms community.
So I think everyone knows what a hash function is.
It takes some value like a string,
and maps it into something like a string or an integer.
And the hash value is much smaller than item.
Hash collisions are when two distinct items
map to the same hash.
So when you look at hash functions,
There are really fancy hash functions which
are cryptographic in nature.
These are collision-resistant using cryptography and Bitcoin
and things like that.
And then there are these faster ones,
which are used for hash tables, where hash collisions aren't
the end of the world.
And so we'll be using these.
So take a string and map it to some values.
That's what hash functions do.
OK.
So exact duplication is conceptually very simple.
You take a string, you see if there's an exact match,
and you remove all but one.
So here you have a bunch of elements, and you hash them,
and you dedupe.
And exact duplication is very nice.
It's very clear what's happening.
But this isn't really good enough for the messy web data
because often you have these near duplicates.
And one note is that there are many ways to have written this.
This is written in a bit of a MapReduce style
way, which makes it more easily parallelizable and scale.
So, C4, this paper from the T5 paper, which processed Common Crawl,
did exact deduplication.
The items they operate on were three-sentence spans,
and you do an exact match, and they remove all but one.
So if you're paying attention, you
realize that there's something a bit
strange about this because you're looking
at three-sentence spans.
And if you find two documents with three-sentence spans
and you remove all but one, that means
you're just going to rip out three sentences
from that document, which is a little bit strange,
because it breaks the coherence.
But this is what they did.
So that's exact deduplication.
So how do we do near deduplication?
So first of all, we have to define what
approximate match means here.
So to do that, we're going to define this called Jaccard
similarity, which is a fairly standard notion.
And Jaccard of two sets is basically
the size of the intersection over the size of the union.
So given these two sets--
1, 2, 3, 4, and 1, 2, 3, 5, when you compute Jaccard,
you take the intersection.
That's 1, 2, 3.
You take the union, that's 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
and you divide, and Jaccard is 0.6.
So Jaccard is a number between 0 and 1.
0 means that they're disjoint, 1 means that they're identical.
So a fairly natural notion.
And we're going to say that two documents are
near duplicates if their Jaccard similarity is
above some threshold, let's say 0.99.
So now the question is, how do you find near duplicates
in linear time?
So fortunately, this is a solved algorithms question.
And the answer is to use MinHash.
Well, OK.
So the first step is to use MinHash.
That's not the final answer.
So MinHash is a random hash function,
so that the probability of a hash collision
is exactly the Jaccard of A and B.
So this is a very nice property because hashing
is good for making things linear time.
Jaccard is the metric that we want,
and we're connecting these two right now in expectation.
So what's interesting is normally,
you want hash functions to define hash functions
so that everything is hashing--
distinct elements are hashing to different things.
You don't want collisions.
But here you actually want collisions--
not arbitrary collisions, but you
want to control the collisions in a certain way
to align with the similarity.
So similar things you want to collide
more than disparate things.
So the MinHash is essentially, actually, let's see.
Maybe I will-- so here's the MinHash.
It's fairly simple.
You take a set, and you hash every element in that set,
and you take the minimum element.
So if you're seeing this for the first time,
it may seem a little bit strange.
Why are you taking the min?
You can take the max, too.
It doesn't really matter.
It's just a way to break ties.
So here's the picture that you should have in your mind.
So if you have A, remember A contains 1, 2, 3,
4, and B contains 1, 2, 3, 5.
So this is a characteristic matrix representation
of these two sets.
And so what the random hash function is doing
is that it induces a permutation over the items.
So it might be 4, 3, 1, 5, 2, or something else.
And then you look at which item is first,
according to this permutation in A, and which item is first in B.
So each item has the same probability of being first.
So if the random hash function puts 1 first, then first in A
will be equal to first in B. And if it's 2 first,
then it's the same.
If it's 3 first, it's also the same.
But if the random permutation puts 4 first,
then the first element in A is going
to be different from the first element in B, and same with 5.
So look at this representation.
Basically, the random hash function
says elect one of these rows to be first.
And then when the min is just telling me--
the min equal of A equal to min of B
is basically telling me whether that row is the same.
OK.
So that is, I guess, the proof of why this property holds,
which is that you have a hash function in expectation
over your random choice of hash functions,
that the probability of collision
is the similarity metric you want.
OK.
So let's just check this in code.
So I'm going to generate 100 different hash functions.
Each hash function is given by a seed.
And I just check whether the MinHash
is equal to MinHash, and the estimated Jaccard.
So I'm going to just look at the number of the fraction
of matches, and you get 0.6.
And the key thing with the MinHash
is that I don't have to do the n-squared thing.
I can compute the MinHash of A and the MinHash of B and MinHash
of a different set, and I just look for collisions.
Any questions so far about MinHash?
So now we can hash our items, but we're not
done yet because a collision doesn't tell us
the Jaccard is above some threshold, which is what we want.
We want to find A and B such that Jaccard
is greater than 0.99.
All we've done is said, OK, well,
if we've got a collision, the probability of that collision
of two things colliding is the Jaccard.
But that's not really that useful by itself.
It's stochastic, and I can't really
get anything reliable here.
So the next idea is this thing called
locality-sensitive hashing, which essentially
solves this problem.
So this is a very classic idea in theoretical computer science,
and it's quite nice.
The idea here is that we have A and B colliding with probability
equal to the Jaccard.
So it is true that more similar items will collide more often,
but it's very stochastic.
The variance is quite large here.
So our goal is to have A and B collide
if the Jaccard is greater than some threshold.
So we, in some sense, have to sharpen these probabilities
somehow.
The probability can't just be literally equal to the Jaccard.
So the solution is to use more hash functions.
And these hash functions are going to be independent.
So this part gets a bit technical, but we'll walk through it.
So you break the n hash functions
into b bands of r hash functions.
So if you have 12 hash functions, you have three bands,
each band has 4 hash functions.
So there's a band here, h1 through h4.
Here's a second band, h5 through h8.
Third band, h9 through h12.
And then so what we're going to try to do--
so each hash function gives us either a collision
or not collision.
And so every hash function, a probability of colliding.
So the key here is that we want to say, compute the probability
that A and B collide.
We say that A and B collide if for some band
all of its hash functions return the same value.
So if h5 and h6 and h7 and h8 all return the same value--
sorry-- if h5 of A equals h5 of B and h6 of A equals h6 of B
and so on, that means this band is triggered,
and then I would say they're colliding.
Or if this band, if all of these agree,
then I say it's collision, or these two.
But you don't have to have all the hash functions return
the same value.
So there's this and-or structure here
that is doing the lifting here.
And we'll see why this works.
So now let's say you have a particular Jaccard of A and B,
what is the probability that A and B collide
according to this definition?
So we can calculate this.
So let's say that this Jaccard similarity is 0.8.
And we have five bands, and each band has 10 hash functions.
So then we can say, what is the probability of a fixed band
matching?
So that's 0.8 to the r.
Because each band has r hash functions,
so the probability that they all have to match is 0.8 to the r.
So the probability of a fixed band matching
is generally quite low.
It's exponential in r.
And then now the probability of collision
is the probability that some band matches.
And that's going to be the probability of 1
minus the probability of--
so this is the probability of a band not matching.
And if you raise it to the b-- there's
b bands-- there's a probability that all of them don't match.
And then 1 minus that is the probability that some match.
So the probability of collision is 0.4.
And you're expected to be higher because you're
given B tries to get a match.
So if you plot this, this is what it looks like.
So you have on the x-axis the similarity here.
And we were looking at 0.8.
And you look at the probability of a collision here.
So we would expect that if the similarity is 0, then
it should be 0.
If it's 1, it's 1.
But notice that this is an interesting S-shaped, which
is nice because this is what we wanted to sharpen.
We wanted to basically say, if the similarity is
below some threshold, then we want the probability to match
to be as low as possible.
And if the similarity is above some threshold,
we want it to be as high as possible.
So we're trying to get this to be like a phase transition.
And if you plot this function as a function of similarity,
that's what you get.
OK.
So let's just look at some examples.
So concretely, we have similarity 0.7 to 0.98.
And we're going to look at how b equals 10, r equals 10.
So we look at the collision probability,
according to our definition.
And we see that this gives us a range of 0.25 to 1.
So if you were to set a threshold, this is not so bad.
We can set it here.
And these with some probability will--
they're still false positives because, even if these
are below a threshold, let's say 0.9, they might still collide.
But we can filter them out if we want.
But the ones above are mostly kept.
So what happens when you move--so increasing r.
So remember, r is the number of hash functions within a bucket.
So when you increase r, the threshold
sharpens and moves the curve to the right.
Everything becomes harder to match
because you have more hash functions inside a bucket that
sharpens that exponent.
So the probability you see are sharper here,
and now everything moves to the right.
And now it's fairly unlikely that if something
has a low Jaccard, you're going to match it.
So before it was 0.25, and now it's 0.008.
So we're sharpening the probabilities.
And then increasing b has the effect
of moving the curve to the left.
It makes it easier to match. b is the number of bands.
And some band has to match.
If you have more bands, then there's
more chances of matching.
So if you look at this, then before and after.
So now we're making-- before this, 0.9 was only 0.72,
and now it's 0.92.
And of course, this also increases, but not by that much.
And you can drive these phase transitions
to be as sharp as you want by increasing b and r.
But of course, if you can increase b and r too much,
then it can be more expensive.
So let's look at a more real-world setting.
So in this paper on de-duplication,
they had b, 20 bands, and r is 450.
So it give you an idea of the magnitude of these numbers.
And in general, the phase transition happens
at a threshold, which is 1/b b raised to the power of 1/r.
So if you want to filter based on Jaccard greater than 0.9,
then you basically have to set b and r such that this is 0.9.
And then by changing b and r, you
can make that phase transition sharper.
So remember the probability of the fixed band matches is 1/b.
If you are at this threshold, then the probability
that A and B collide is approximately--it's a constant.
So the probability of collision is 0.64.
And this makes sense.
So basically, if you have a phase transition,
the center of that phase transition is 0.64.
And everything below it should go to 0, as b and r increases,
and everything above, it should go to 1 as b and r increases.
Any questions about LSH?
So this method is called MinHash LSH because LSH really
works for any hash functions.
For de-duplication language model processing,
we're using the MinHash, which approximates Jaccard.
And so that basically is the one you should use here.
Questions about dedupe?
So one note about dedupe is that there's often, as we'll see,
data sets that are coming in.
And sometimes the de-duplication will happen within a data set.
But you actually have to do de-duplication
across your entire data set because often data sets can
be redundant.
So sometimes that's not done, but it should be.
Let's go on to the next topic, which is data mixing.
So far, we've transformed our data from really raw HTML
or PDFs into text.
We filtered for high-quality.
We deduped, so we have a smaller set of high-quality documents.
And this generally happens for a given data source.
But language models are trained on multiple data sources.
So in Marin, currently, this website
tracks the different data sources
that the next model will be trained on.
And you can see that there's a bunch of things.
There's Nemotron, there's FinePDFs, which we talked about.
There's some institutional books, and some code,
and all these things.
So you have all these different sources.
And the question is, how do you combine these?
So if you look at an older paper, The Pile,
this is the set of sources that they had at that time.
And they essentially assign a particular weight
to each component.
So basically, you have a distribution over sources.
So where does that weight come from?
So just cut and dry.
Let's say you have three sources.
You want to find a data mixture, and a data mixture
is just a distribution over your sources.
So if you're just thinking about this problem
from first principles--
well, not from first principles, but just from what you might do.
Vibes, which is, I guess, the opposite of first principles,
is you just manually set it based
on some intuition, which is more often than you might think,
what people do.
So I think this is definitely fairly vibes-based.
And even more recent papers, you just look at--
maybe you use some method and then you just tweak things.
You can also do uniform sampling, which
is you just put a uniform distribution over your sources,
and you sample every chunk.
You just sample a source.
You can also do proportional mixing,
which is that you sample proportional
to the number of tokens in a source.
So if you have a data set with more tokens,
then you put a higher weight.
So this is also generally a rational thing to do.
But you might worry that if you have a huge, low-quality data
set, that's going to eat up a lot of your tokens.
So it doesn't seem quite optimal either.
So intuitively, you should upweight your higher quality
sources.
But there's two things that are important to keep in mind.
One is that you do want to ensure some diversity.
So often, sources are incomparable for literature,
code, and papers.
You can't really say that this paper
is higher quality than this code because they're just
incomparable objects, maybe.
And if you want your language model to do well,
you don't want to just put all your mass on papers.
The second thing, which I will talk a bit more about,
is each source is actually finite.
So if you put too much weight on a small source,
then you essentially run out of that source,
and you need to just epoch over it,
meaning that you keep on training literally the same tokens.
And this is going to be bad for reasons we'll see.
OK.
So let's try to unpack this a little bit more concretely,
this last point.
So imagine you just have two sources--
a low-quality source, you have 10 trillion tokens,
and you have a high-quality source
that has 10 billion tokens.
Generally, high-quality sources are smaller.
So if you just do a naive data mixture.
Let's just do uniform.
So half on high, half on low.
And I'm going to train for 1 trillion tokens.
So when I say train for 1 trillion,
that doesn't mean unique tokens.
It just means train for that many steps divided
by batch size, essentially, or times batch size.
So then let's look at this, which
is the number of times a particular element
in the low-quality data set was trained on.
So that's the number of epochs a particular data
point was trained on.
So a p low times the trained tokens
is the number of times I want to request tokens
from this low-quality source, and divided by the total number
of low-quality sources.
So this is less than 1.
So basically, that means 5% of the tokens
in this low-quality data set, I'm
going to touch and train on once.
And then if you look at high quality,
you'll see that the number of epochs
is 50, because I only have 10 billion tokens here.
And if I'm half-half, that means 500 billion tokens--
I need to train up 500 billion tokens of high-quality data.
But I don't have 500 billion tokens of data,
so I have to repeat each data point 50 times.
So this is actually really important.
And some big model runs have messed this up.
You can't just naively look at the data sets
and define a distribution and then
you sample, because if you just look at the quality,
if you look at the data, you're missing
how many data points are there.
Does this make sense?
Maybe pause for questions.
This is an important point.
Yeah.
I guess, for the high-quality data, [INAUDIBLE]
as [INAUDIBLE] low quality.
Why do you need 50 epochs in the first place?
Doesn't it achieve comparable performance
at a level that is way fewer?
Yeah.
So the question is, why do you need 50 epochs?
And I guess the point is that you don't need 50 epochs.
Worst case, it's wasting compute.
Sorry, best case is wasting compute, and worst case,
you're overfitting.
The reason it's 50 is that if you just go in
and you define this data mixture,
then you're going to end up doing
50 epochs without realizing it, unless you're
paying close attention.
So this is basically--
the lesson is look at how many epochs you're actually
doing on your data.
Yeah.
How do the mixtures get expressed during training?
When you switch every step, you train steps of 10, saying,
oh, I want to do 10, Python code, 10 essays,
because I feel like-- is there also any intuition between what
decisions are made there?
Yeah.
Good question.
So the question is, when you train,
how do the mixtures get realized?
And so, in general, you just sample.
So you want to fill a batch.
So you can sample essentially for each element which mixture
component it comes from.
And you fill up a batch with sequences
from that mixture component.
Usually, every sequence comes from one mixture component.
You're not sampling per token.
So each batch should be mixed.
So I guess the mixture assumptions
are at the batch level, and then you train for that.
It's not like, oh, it's one step is-- the code in one step is--
Yeah.
In general, you want to reduce variance.
You want to train for multiple--
batch should have some mixture.
OK.
So this problem has been noticed quite a long time ago.
And so in this paper, they introduced the UniMax.
And in that case, they were training in multilingual models.
And it was very clear that some languages
were very low-resource, so you had to do something about this.
So, in this paper, they noticed that before some works
would essentially take the proportional mixing
and raise it to some power to flatten it out the distribution.
But the idea in this paper is that let's be
a bit more explicit about that.
Let's sample the sources uniformly,
but with a hard cap on the number of epochs.
So this is the key idea.
Here, you say I'm only going to take 20 epochs
over a particular data source.
So if you've done that, then too bad.
You don't get any more tokens.
You move on to the next thing.
So this is like a safety net in some sense.
So in particular, if you look at the number, the probability
assigned to a source times the number of training tokens,
that should be less than or equal to the cap.
And there's a simple procedure for actually determining
the mixture subject to this constraint.
So let's switch gears a little bit and talk
about how we define the mixture in the first place,
because if you have 50 sources, there's
50 numbers you have to fill.
And we notice that proportional mixing isn't really enough.
Maybe you can try to estimate some quality metric,
and then you can sample proportional to that,
but that is also heuristic.
So the most principled methods and most
easiest to understand what's happening
is these regression-based mixing methods, or RegMix, Olmix,
and other papers like this.
And the idea here is relatively simple.
So first, let's say you're trying
to train a large-scale model.
So you go to a small scale, let's say
300 million parameters, and you try different data mixtures.
So let's say you have three components.
You try different mixtures.
And then you train these small models.
You train a swarm of small models.
Each model gives you a loss on some target metric.
It could be some downstream values.
It could be perplexity, whatever you want.
So then you use these data points to basically fit
a regression where the regression model maps
these inputs, which is the data mixture weights, to the loss.
So now you have basically a very cheap model that tells you,
if I were to train on this mixture, what loss do I get?
Then you can essentially optimize that data mixture--
sorry-- optimize that function for the optimal data mixture.
And then that is the data mixture
you use to train the large-scale model.
So that's the simple procedure.
And you notice some similarities with scaling laws,
where you're trying to do some cheap computations to figure out
some answers, and then scale up.
OK.
So there's a few design decisions here.
One is, what are the mixtures that you're trying out here?
You need a distribution over distributions here.
So often, people use some Dirichlet distribution.
You also have to define the regression method.
People have tried linear models or boosted decision trees.
You have to figure out the target here.
Often this is based on downstream evals.
But you have to be very careful not to overfit because we're
doing pretraining.
Supposedly, pretraining is supposed
to be training this general-purpose model,
and we're not trying to fit some downstream evals.
And if you're not careful, for example,
if you have a bunch of code evals, then, well, guess what?
You're going to upweight all the code data.
That's not rocket science.
And if you then go and you say, I want to generate some poetry,
you might realize that you've overfit.
So you have to be very careful about that.
So proportional mixing and uniform mixing
don't have this problem because you're not looking.
There's no downstream evals.
And the final thing is, how much of a difference
between small and large scale is there?
And this is a cost and accuracy trade-off.
Of course, if you train really, really small models,
this might not be representative.
But if you train large models to do this,
well, there's no point in doing any of this.
You just train.
You're basically doing hyperparameter tuning.
at the largest scale, which is too expensive.
So this Olmix paper actually has this nice table,
which shows you for a number of different methods
that all fall into this framework.
The size of the proxy models.
They're generally fairly tens of millions of parameters.
How many mixtures do you sample?
m here being the number of parameters in your mixture--
sorry-- the number of domains rather.
And you can use Dirichlet.
You can use exponential.
And then the regression model, you
can fit a log-linear model, which tends to work pretty well.
And then you can use different ways
to solve this optimization problem.
So there's two leaps of faith here
that you just have to be very careful of is
that the regression model was trained
on a bunch of these small proxy runs,
and you're optimizing this.
So the hope is that the minimizer, your optimal data
mixture, that regression model is still accurate.
And this is a little bit of-- you
have to be very careful because if you, let's say,
sample a random mixture, you'll probably be fine because
of classic generalization.
You sample a mixture, and you fit a function,
it should be able to predict in distribution.
But when you're optimizing, you're
essentially trying to go to potentially the extremes
where you might not have as much coverage.
So that's one thing to be careful of.
And the other thing is that optimal data mixtures,
you just hope that they transfer from small scale to large scale.
And this, in general, it seems like at least at the scales
that open community works with, it
tends to be true or not plainly false.
But clearly, there are scale-dependent effects.
If you just think about the previous slide
when we were talking about filtering,
if you're training for many more tokens,
then probably low-quality data is OK.
So clearly, the optimum is not the same,
but you just hope for the best here.
OK.
So hold on.
There's one scale-dependent effect
that we already talked about that we
need to address here, which is that, imagine,
so we have a lot of low-quality data, 10 trillion tokens,
10 billion tokens of high-quality data.
And if we train a small model on low token counts,
do you remember?
What happens is that you might— this is a made-up example,
but you might put a lot of mass on your high-quality data,
because low token counts, you're not epoching.
So it's like, oh, wow, Wikipedia is so great.
Let's just train on Wikipedia.
But if you then go and train this large model
on this mixture, then you're going
to end up epoching a lot on this high-quality data,
and you'll overfit.
And that's definitely bad.
So one way to fix this, which is done in this Olmix paper,
is you can just cap the number of epochs.
So that is one solution.
There's another solution here, which goes
by probably multiple names.
But one name for it is simulated epoching.
And the principle here is that make your small scale
look like your large scale.
This is a general theme for the course.
We saw it when we talked about muP.
You parameterize your model so that your hyperparameters
transfer.
And so the same principle applies here.
And the problem with doing this naive scaling
is that you can't be not epoching out small scale then
epoching at large scales, because then those
are qualitatively different operations on your dataset.
So the way you would handle this is you downstream your sources
proportionally.
So if you have your small runs, over 10 billion tokens,
and your big run with one trillion tokens,
then you have a 1 in 100 downsampling.
And then you basically use the downsample mixture.
And so the idea is that if you have the downsampled data, then
this solution is not going to look good because you're not
training on all--you don't get to just train on Wikipedia.
You're going to train on some minuscule fraction of Wikipedia,
and you'll realize, oh, actually,
I'm going to be epoching a lot.
And that's going to have a really bad loss, which
means that in the optimization, you're
going to look for more balanced approaches.
So you're simulating the data scarcity
that you would get in your high regime at low scale.
So to summarize this section, the problem
is how do you weight different sources?
Wikipedia, you have your Common Crawl.
You have your code.
You have some math data that you scraped from somewhere.
How do you balance them?
Regression-based mixing is a nice framework,
I think, to think about things.
You estimate your function form that maps your mixture weights
to a loss at small scale, optimize,
and then you generalize to large scale.
And you just have to be very careful with this
because of epoching and overfitting issues.
And you have to either use cap epoching or simulate epoching.
So one lesson here is that if you're
trying to optimize anything, you have
to be very careful because you are in danger
of optimizing the wrong thing.
Any questions about data mixing before we move on?
When you're done sampling, is there
something too small that you can't really generalize as well?
So the question is, if you're downsampling, is there a risk?
Maybe you get too small of a data set.
Yeah, absolutely.
So I think you might get into a case
where you just have so few tokens.
I think then what will happen is that your optimum will just
put a very small mass on that.
And when you scale up, maybe you get the right set of tokens.
So in principle, it should work out.
But there might be rounding errors where you end up,
instead of training once on this data set,
you train like zero times by accident.
But you can work around these by just--
then you always train once on this data.
OK.
Yeah.
In data mixing, I guess these sources just happen
to align with different topics.
But do you ever take a diverse data set
and try to do data mixing within that?
Yeah.
So the question is, what do you apply data mixing to?
Different domains or even within a data set?
Actually, I forgot to mention that,
so I'm glad you brought it up.
So in Nemotron paper, they actually
install the [INAUDIBLE] stuff as well.
You basically think about-- let's say
I give you just Common Crawl.
You can actually break this up, so you can group by domain.
So the IT folks have this web organizer,
so you can group into topics.
But you can also quality filter.
So then you have this two-dimensional grid
where you have domains, and you have quality.
And each of these cells is something that you would data mix.
So that's one automatic way to determine the domains.
And then on top of that, you add extra sources
that people hand you.
So I'm going to quickly go through post-training data here.
So up until now, this is basically pre-training or maybe
mid-training data.
It's generally fairly task agnostic,
except for the RegMix stuff where you're
trying to minimize the loss.
But the data itself is still relatively task agnostic,
and you're trying to develop basic skills.
So when you look at post-training, a lot of the data
becomes very task-dependent.
And I'm not going to do a comprehensive review.
I just want to point out some interesting post-training data
sets that have been recently released,
in particular, for coding, since that's of great interest
these days.
So the general recipe is you define a set of environments.
In this case, think about code, which might be GitHub repos.
You define a set of tasks or prompts,
and then you collect responses from a strong model or teacher.
So implicitly, at least in the open community,
almost all the post-training data, most of it,
is synthetically generated.
You can also replace a strong model with a human,
but that is slow and costs a lot of money.
But, if you're at the frontier--
a few years ago, you had to go and pay a lot of people a lot
of money to give you responses.
And nowadays, even at the frontier,
you can do hybrid human-AI things.
But anyway, the point is that there's some teacher out there
that's giving you responses.
OK.
So I'm just going to talk to a few works here.
So one is this work called OpenThoughts.
And this idea here is--this came around.
It was motivated by when o1 came out,
and there was a lot of attention on reasoning, mostly
for math and science.
How do we get really good post-training data sets for this?
And they eventually came out with 1.2 million examples
using this teacher model.
So the steps are, first of all, there are a bunch of--
So what are the environments and the tasks and questions?
There are a lot of different sources that they drew from.
There are human sources like Stack Exchange, or NuminaMath,
and then there's some synthetic sources as well.
These are just a subset of the coding ones,
but there's also more for math and chemistry.
This is a big project that involved
a lot of different contributions from many people.
So you can see that some of these are coding exercises.
Some of these are more realistic things that show up on--
I guess, CodeGolf is not realistic,
but there are some more realistic examples here.
So code review, this is probably more realistic.
And they did a fairly comprehensive analysis of,
given this data set, how do you generate responses?
They show that having a few sources
was actually better than trying to do all sources.
Sampling multiple generations is helpful, like 16.
One thing that was interesting is that having better models
aren't necessarily better teachers.
So for example, QwQ-32B, which is now a very old and small
model, was a better teacher than DeepSeek-R1,
which was at the time probably one
of the strongest open models.
They also found that basic answer filtering wasn't helpful.
And so the entire data pipeline looks something
like this, where you have a bunch of these sources going in,
and then you deduplicate.
You randomly sample.
I guess this downsamples the questions,
and you generate multiple answers,
and that gets into the final data set.
So the 1.2 million is examples, but divided by 16
gives you the number of actual questions.
So that was for math and science and some code.
I think more recently there's been
a lot of interest in developing, in particular, agentic coding
models-- so not just a model that can just
generate some code, but actually a model that
can do software development.
So this SWE-smith paper had the idea of-- you're
given a repository, you're using a language model
to automatically generate tasks.
So they have an agent that takes a repository
and actually makes it usable for installing dependencies
and so on.
And then you generate tasks which are generally--
you modify the code in some way and maybe introduce some bugs.
And those get verified, and you get task instances.
So these are synthetic tasks, but you get 50k of them,
which is actually at the time, which was last year,
quite large.
So since then, there's been a bunch of other work, which
I'll mention.
So there's this SWE-Zero paper from NVIDIA, which had this--
actually, OK, I'll also talk about that.
So this is an interesting idea where the observation
was that, unlike math, SWE tasks have
a lot of heavy dependencies.
Most GitHub repos like don't even run.
And you have to install all these dependencies.
They're out of date, especially if you roll back
to when a PR was just a mess.
And this is just a nightmare.
And so they were thinking about, how can
we actually get a data set on all the repos?
And rather than having a repo-specific Docker image,
they noticed that the models are actually good enough
that they can solve a lot of these tasks
without execution feedback.
So if you look at some of these models,
if you were allowing execution, you get 80.
If you don't allow execution, you get almost 70,
which is not bad for not being able to execute code.
So somehow these models have some internal semantics of code.
So they were able to generate 300,000 agent trajectories.
All of these are real GitHub PRs,
so they're realistic on the SWE-smith examples.
They use the OpenHands scaffold.
There's a lot of details how to prevent agent hacking.
So normally, you hand an agent this instruction.
You explore, you test, you implement.
And SWE-Zero version was basically saying you cannot run
Python code.
You can only do set, grep, and all these basic operations.
OK.
So then they distilled from big Qwen model
and filtered because sometimes the Qwen model
will ignore these instructions and still try to execute anyway.
And then they show that with this--
oh, they also had a 13k agent trajectories that do require
execution feedback.
So they train models where they first
fine-tune on these SWE-Zero examples,
and then fine-tune again on these SWE-Zero examples.
And they were able to--
I guess the frontier is still pretty high up,
but they were able to make some progress here.
I'll quickly go through SWE-rebench,
which is essentially another attempt
to grab tons and tons of PRs.
And all of these look, get a bunch of GitHub repos,
try to install the repo.
Most of them probably failed and try harder.
And then you use a language model to give you the responses.
And these actually just came out today.
So you can take this SWE-Zero idea,
and you can now scale up to 12 million agent trajectories.
The nice benefit of SWE-Zero is that it's very lightweight.
Here, they use the SWE-rebench tasks.
So in this one, remember, they were trying
to get things to execute.
They only got 32,000 of them to execute,
and 120 of them didn't execute.
But SWE-Zero doesn't care.
You can use all of them.
This is a very small model because-- now this data set
is quite large.
And so I think, as you can see, the data sets
are getting more and more sophisticated.
You go from environment-free things like math to now coding.
And now the coding data sets are growing quite a bit.
But the general idea is that you have these prompts, which
there's trade-offs.
You can have fully synthetic.
You can have semi-synthetic, where
you have real environment and synthetic tasks,
or you can have real.
And the responses generally are coming from just capable models,
but they also need to be good teachers.
Code environments are a pain.
And there's a lot of filtering and other details which
we don't have time for.
OK.
To summarize this lecture, we talked about filtering.
So define what good looks like, and then train
a lightweight classifier.
Go over your web crawl, and you can
get a small subset that matches what you're looking for.
De-duplication is important to avoid overfitting and saving
flops.
Mixing.
Try a mixture at small scales, extrapolate to large scale.
And then we looked at some posttraining data.
I will say, though, that a lot of the data work
can be very grungy.
It's very domain-specific and requires
looking at concrete examples to make these high-quality data
sets.
So this lecture is not really representative of what
data work is like, but hopefully giving you
an idea of the data landscape out there.
OK.
So that will be it for today.
[APPLAUSE]